<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Independencie Gods veritie: or, The necessitie of toleration. Unto which is added the chief principles of the government of independent churches. / Written by J.G. B.D.</title>
            <author>Goodwin, John, 1594?-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85398</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1173</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E410_24</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204458</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863948</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863948</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161216</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85398)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161216)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 65:E410[24])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Independencie Gods veritie: or, The necessitie of toleration. Unto which is added the chief principles of the government of independent churches. / Written by J.G. B.D.</title>
                  <author>Goodwin, John, 1594?-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Ley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>J.G. = John Goodwin.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "8ber: [i.e. October] 14th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Independent churches --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religious tolerance --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161216:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>INDEPENDENCIE GODS VERITIE: OR, THE NECESSITIE OF TOLERATION.</p>
            <p>Unto which is added the chief Principles of the Government of INDEPENDENT CHURCHES.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>J. G.</hi> B. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Ley</hi> 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:161216:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:161216:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Independency Gods Veritie:</hi> OR, The neceſsity of <hi>Toleration.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I Am not ignorant, that I am now entring the field, where many Combatants ſtand ready to encounter me; but I hope the judicious Reader will not lay the crime of preſumption to my charge becauſe I undertake in one ſingle ſheet, to vindicate that which whole volumes have calumniated, nor that I devulge my thoughts in the defence of that which of late was ſo much oppoſed, even that which ſo many learned and pious men, ſurviving at this preſent, both in Towne and City, in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Army, have ſeen to their grief trampled under foot, and to their joy exalted.</p>
            <p>Many there are who hurried on with the violent ſtream of their paſſiions, if they but once hear Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency named with applauſe, like a gald horſe, winch and kick, and bear down all before them: <hi>Edwards, Vicars,</hi> and <hi>Baſtwick,</hi> have wrote much but proved little or nothing of what they undertook; but like ſome unskilfull Statuaries, who in framing a Coloſſus, if they make it ſtraddle wide, look big, and gape, they imagine they have equalled Apelles his Maſter-piece; ſo they, binding in one volume a whole bundle of invectives, framed againſt that,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:161216:3"/>
which in truth they are not able to oppugne, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive they have framed pieces both laſting and inimitable.</p>
            <p>The grand Engin with which our adverſaries would beat downe Independency, is that Text of Scripture, <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. every one of you ſaith, <hi>I am of Paul, I of Cephas, and I of Chriſt:</hi> But alas! they doe not conſider, that this place maketh altogether againſt them; for in theſe words, we are given to underſtand, that there were in the Primitive times divers Churches and Congregations under ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Paſtors, S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth not tax their manner of order, but reproveth thoſe contentious ſpirits, that vaunted themſelves to be under a more reall Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor then others were, as that <hi>Paul</hi> exceeded <hi>Apollos</hi> in the gifts of the Spirit, <hi>Apollos Cephas,</hi> and a third depraving them all, and cauſing a Schiſme, boaſting hee and thoſe of his faction were the onely followers of Chriſt: ſome there are that imploy theſe words of S. <hi>Paul Cor.</hi> 10. to extirpate Independency root and branch, where he ſaith, <hi>Now I beſeech you Brethren, by the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that you all ſpeak the ſame thing, and that there be no diviſions amongſt you.</hi> I anſwer, that for us to take this ſaying of S. <hi>Paul</hi> as a Precept, that all men muſt be of one beleefe, and ſpeak one thing, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous; for it is impoſſible and cannot be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, but that while there are different men, there will be different minds, and that wil ſeem good and right to ſome, which to others will appeare errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and impious.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:161216:3"/>Therefore Saint Paul muſt be underſtood other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then ſo, and to that end, we ought to conſider that S Paul giveth this precept in reference to their temporall actions as well as their ſpirituall perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances, as it were perſwading them to pollicy, leſt by their diviſions and factions, the heathen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt they then were converſant, might have juſt occaſion to deſpiſe their Worſhip, and fit op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to injure their perſons; but let us grant that he ſpake to them wholly, in reference to their ſpirituall performances; yet it will not follow, that the Church of God ought to be tied in one knot, and kneaded in one lump; for the Church of God, though divided into diſtinct Congregations, as they were in the Primitive time, may ſpeak one and the ſame thing, although in different manner; and like birds that ſing divers notes yet make one harmony agree in one thing, though diverſly deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered: beſides if it were, as theſe men would have it, who profeſſe themſelves utter enemies to Tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that every Chriſtian by theſe words, ought to be compelled to give outward obedience to what is injoyned, what ſundry grievous, and dire inconveniencies may happen I ſhall ſet down:</p>
            <p>Firſt, That ſervice cannot be acceptable to God which is not performed with a willing mind, and a curſe lies on him that dosthe work of the Lord neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently, which muſt inevitably happen if this courſe were taken, to tyranize over mens Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by compelling them, to do that which their Conſcience alloweth not, they ſin againſt the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:161216:4"/>
cleer and deſtinate light of knowledge, and ſo in part are guilty of the ſin of the holy Ghoſt; but now that all men may have a good conceit of us, and be incorporated with us, let him conſider;</p>
            <p>Firſt, What a ſweet and heavenly communion we have amongſt our ſelves, how nothing is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted prejudiciall to tender Conſciences; who though perhaps not reſolved in ſome points, yet Chriſt who alone ought to rule his Church, we know in his good time will informe them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That though we acknowledge Chriſt to be the only ruler of his Church, yet ye deveſt not the temporal Magiſtrate of his power to puniſh all groſſe crimes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That we allow none to be capable of our Member-ſhip, till we have had a ſufficient triall of their Converſation, and have heard the confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Faith, and the evidences of the truth of their converſion, and till they have entred into a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Covenant, and have the joynt aſſent of the whole Congregation, whereby we come as neer as in us lies, to the forme obſerved by the Church at Jeruſalem, Act. 1. 15.</p>
            <p>But on the other ſide conſider, our adverſaries, who are continually at variance amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, how they conſtraine tender Conſciences to obey their rigorous and Anti-chriſtian commands, how they beſtow on the temporal Magiſtrate, the office belonging only to Chriſt, how they admit of all perſons whatſoever without the leaſt examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, how their Miniſters do deny, exclaime, and preach againſt Chriſts kingly Government, how
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:161216:4"/>
they and all the people under their Miniſtery, are unconverted, or at leaſt but in part, wanting the main thing, to wit, Chriſts kingly office, men vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly out of the Covenant of Grace, who have not ſo much, as an outward profeſſion of Faith, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Chriſt to be their king.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The neceſsity of Toleration.</head>
               <p>PResbitery, is the rivall of Epiſcopacy, but In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependency is of another ſtraine, and admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not of humane prudence in Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: for the Church which is of a ſpirituall buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, framed of ſuch lively ſtones, as are not of the world, nor of the wiſdome of the world, but foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded only upon the wiſdom of God, revealed in the word by his Spirit, is ſufficient to conſtitute and and maintain a Church without any aſſiſtance from the Kingdomes of the world, whoſe power they leave intire to it ſelf, for the Biſhops, and Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, by their Church pollicy, ſtand Compettitors with the Magiſtrate, to whom we leave all ſave on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the kingdome of Chriſt, (which himſelf hath ſaid) is not of this world, and ſo can be no trouble to it, unleſſe it be firſt troubled by it.</p>
               <p>But as the caſe ſtands now at preſent, Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency is the only line that can ſtanch our wounds, the only damme that can ſtay the inundation of blood, which is elſe likely to overwhelme us; for the very name of Presbitery, is hatefull to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and it were too ſtrange a relapſe to give them againe their Biſhops and their Litturgy, and if ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the other be permitted, there can be nothing expected but murmurings, and claſhings, if not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:161216:5"/>
mutinings, but if a Toleration were allowed, it would take away all occaſions of tumults and Garboiles, for when every man is permitted to uſe his Conſcience according as he is perſwaded in himſelfe, they will eſteem their burthens not halfe ſo heavy as before, and be incouraged to yeild o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to thoſe injunctions impoſed on them by their Rulers, which otherwiſe is not to be expected from them; ſo that it is not only convenient, but alſo very neceſſary that there be a Toleration.</p>
               <p>Again, any man the leaſt inlightned will diſpenſe with any compulſive ordinance more tamely, then when he is conſtrained in point of Religion, and we know well that the originall of our late Warre was the Biſhops aſſuming to themſelves that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, which Chriſt never gave them, to wit, Of compelling men to yeild obedience to what ever they impoſed; and men now, are grown more va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in their opinions then ever before, and will be as eaſily perſwaded to forſake their meat, as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linguiſh their Tenets; and moreover, it is come to that paſſe, but by what meanes I will not queſtion, that every man eſteemeth it as properly his own, as any Immunity contained in Magna Charta, to uſe his Conſcience without controule; and when they ſhall be debarred of what they have ſo long injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſo much covet to keep, what they may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt let the wiſe judge; therefore there is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a reaſon, but alſo a neceſſity of Toleration.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
